Guide to the Abraham Robinson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Abraham Robinson papers
1918-1988
MS 826
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
The papers consist of correspondence and writings which document Abraham Robinson's professional life and work. Draft and printed copies of Robinson's books and papers comprise the bulk of the papers. Student memorabilia, diaries, and biographical material are also included in the papers.
Robinson, Abraham, 1918-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Renee Robinson, 1976-1992; and acquired from the Jewish National and University Library, 1993.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Writings. II. Correspondence and Other Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Abraham Robinson Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and memorabilia, which document the professional career of Abraham Robinson. The papers also include a smaller quantity of personal and family papers. Manuscripts and printed copies of Robinson's articles and books comprise the bulk of the papers. There is very little correspondence in the papers, most of which dates from the last few years of Robinson's life. Renee Robinson donated her husband's papers to the Yale University Library between 1976 and 1993.
Series I, WRITINGS, begins with the three volume printed copy of Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson. The folders following these volumes contain manuscripts, printed copies, and notes for the many books and papers by Robinson. The folders are arranged in order according to the bibliography published in Selected Papers, with books coming first, papers next, followed by films, and encyclopaedia articles. Numbers in parentheses following the titles of papers refer to the numbers in the published bibliography. Each numbered paper on the bibliography is represented in Series I.
At the end of the series are folders which contain writings not listed in the bibliography. These include book reviews by Robinson, manuscripts, print or near print items, and notes, as well as course material from the several institutions at which Robinson taught. The book reviews come first, followed by the other unlisted writings. The titles for these writings are derived from notes or labels on the manuscripts. They are arranged in chronological order. Course materials, including lecture notes and examination questions, are arranged at the very end of the series and are identified by institution and course title where possible.
Series II, CORRESPONDENCE AND OTHER PAPERS BY AND ABOUT ABRAHAM ROBINSON, includes all papers, other than writings, donated to the Yale University Library. These include materials created by Robinson as well as family records collected by him. In addition there are materials about Robinson collected by Mrs. Robinson to document the life and achievements of her husband and to facilitate the work of those compiling the biographical and analytical sections in Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson.
The series begins with Robinson's correspondence, most of which dates from the last decade of Robinson's life. Correspondence is in English, Hebrew, and German. References to Robinson's publications are included in the exchanges with publishers and co-authors. There is also correspondence relating to Robinson's work with professional organizations, notably the Association for Symbolic Logic, letters concerning professional appointments under the names of various institutions, and invitations to deliver papers at other institutions and conferences.
The remainder of the series is arranged alphabetically by record type. Some of this material such as notecards concerning mathematical bibliography, programs and announcements for Robinson's lectures, reviews of Robinson's published work, and honors and award certificates, diplomas and citations, dates from Robinson's lifetime. Of particular interest are diaries Robinson kept. In one from 1933, written in German, Robinson recorded the experience of fleeing Nazi Germany, from Breslau to Berlin, Munich, and then to Italy. In a second diary or reminiscence, written in Hebrew, Robinson recorded his impressions of life in France during the winter of 1940 and then of his escape to England after the Nazi invasion in June. Other papers in Robinson's hand include student notes in German and Hebrew. Several documents including identity cards and military orders date from Robinson's service with the Free French and British military forces.
Other material in the series dates from after Robinson's death in 1974. This material includes correspondence of Mrs. Robinson, letters of condolence, reminiscences of Abraham Robinson, and programs and remarks from memorial services, dedication ceremonies, and conferences in memory of Abraham Robinson. Published material which refers to Abraham Robinson's life and work, both from his lifetime and after his death, is also collected in this series.
Biographical / Historical
Abraham Robinson was born on October 6, 1918, in Waldenburg, Germany. His father Abraham Robinsohn was a writer, philosopher, and ardent Zionist, who died just prior to his son's birth. The family moved to Breslau in 1925, and when Robinson was fourteen, he emigrated with his mother Hedwig Lotte Robinsohn and brother Saul to Palestine. He was a student at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem from 1936-1939, where he studied mathematics with Abraham Fraenkel.
In 1939 Robinson won a scholarship to the Sorbonne to continue his studies, but soon after his arrival in Paris the Nazis invaded France. Robinson escaped to England, where he volunteered for the Free French Air Force. In January, 1942, he joined the British forces and was appointed scientific officer in the Ministry of Aircraft Production. He was assigned to the Royal Aircraft Establishment at Farnborough. Robinson's work was in the Structures and Mechanical Engineering Department and later in the Aerodynamics Department. It was during this time that he met his future wife, Renee Kopel. They were married on January 30, 1944.
In 1946 Robinson joined the staff of the newly established College of Aeronautics at Cranfield as a senior lecturer in charge of the teaching of mathematics. His work and publications to this date had qualified him to receive a M.Sc. degree from the Hebrew University. During the immediate post-war years, Robinson was also working on a thesis, "The Metamathematics of Algebraic Systems," under the supervision of P. Dienes of Birkbeck College. Robinson received his Ph.D. from the University of London in 1949. From this time on Robinson's research was directed less towards aeronautics and more towards logic and mathematical foundations.
In 1950 Robinson became the deputy head of the department of aerodynamics at the College of Aeronautics, but he left there in 1951 to become an associate professor in the department of applied mathematics at the University of Toronto. In 1956 he was named professor and chairman of the department. His teaching involved a graduate course on wing theory as well as courses in fluid dynamics and partial differential equations. He also continued writing a book on wing theory with a former student J. A. Laurmann, which was published in 1956. His research in logic led to the publication of Theorie Metamematique des Ideaux (1955) and Complete Theories(1956). Robinson also produced papers on model theory and its applications to the theory of algebraically closed fields.
From 1957 until 1962, Robinson taught at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem, occupying the chair in mathematics of his teacher Professor Fraenkel. In Israel, as he did for most of the rest of his life, Robinson devoted himself almost entirely to pure mathematics. His work from his years in Jerusalem and from 1960-1961, which Robinson spent as a visiting professor at Princeton University, were early explorations in nonstandard analysis, a field in which Robinson did pioneering work, and resulted in the publication (1963) of Introduction to Model Theory and the Metamathematics of Algebra.
From the Hebrew University Robinson went on to teach as a professor of mathematics and philosophy at the University of California, Los Angeles (1962-1967) and then as professor and Sterling Professor of mathematics at Yale University (1967-1974). At UCLA Robinson served on the university's Committe on Education Policy and was its chairman during the academic year 1964-1965. He was also a member of the Academic Council which conferred with the president of the University of California system concerning issues involving all nine campuses in the system. Numbers and Ideals (1965), Non-Standard Analysis (1966), and Contributions to Non-Standard Analysis(1972) along with numerous articles were published during these years.
From 1968-1970 Robinson served as president of the Association for Symbolic Logic. He was elected a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1972 and received the Brouwer Medal of the Dutch Mathematical Society in 1973. His election to the National Academy of Sciences was awarded posthumously after his untimely death on April 11, 1974.
For a fuller biography of Abraham Robinson and analysis of Robinson's contributions to applied and pure mathematics, the reader is advised to consult the introductory pages in each of the three volumes of Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson, edited by H. J. Keisler, S. Körner, W. A. J. Luxemburg, and A. D. Young, (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1979). The volumes are included in box 1 of the Abraham Robinson Papers.
Aerodynamics; Logic, Symbolic and mathematical; Nonstandard mathematical analysis; Mathematics -- Study and teaching; Model theory; Diaries; Mathematicians; Robinson, Abraham, 1918-1974; Association for Symbolic Logic; College of Aeronautics (Cranfield, Bedfordshire); Universiṭah ha-ʻIvrit bi-Yerushalayim; University of California, Los Angeles -- Faculty; University of Toronto -- Faculty; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Mathematics
- Writings, 1939-1988; Series I; 5.25' (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged according to the bibliography of Abraham Robinson's writings published in Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson. Writings and notes not listed in this bibliography are arranged at the end of the series.
  - Books
    - Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson, volume 1, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson, volume 2, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Selected Papers of Abraham Robinson, volume 3, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - On the Metamathematics of Algebraic Systems, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - Wing Theory Ia, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Wing Theory Ib, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Wing Theory IIa, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Wing Theory IIb, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Introduction to Model Theory and the Metamathematics of Algebra, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Introduction to Model Theory and the Metamathematics of Algebra, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Introduction to Model Theory and the Metamathematics of Algebra: preface to the Italian edition, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Numbers and Ideas, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Non-Standard Analysis of Normed Space, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Contributions to Non-Standard Analysis, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
    - Non-Standard Analysis: preface to the second edition, Circa 1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Nonarchimedean Fields and Asymptotic Expansions, undated (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
    - Algebra — A Model Theoretic Viewpoint, undated (Box 4, Folder 24a)
  - Papers
    - On the Independence of the Axioms of Definiteness (1), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 24b)
    - On Nil Ideas in General Rings (2), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - On a Certain Variation of the Distributive Law for a Commutative Algebraic Field (3), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Shock Transmission in Beams of Variable Characteristics (4), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - A Minimum Energy Theorem in Aerodynamics (5), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - A Note on the Interpretation of V-G Records (6), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - The Aerodynamic Loading of Wings with Endplates (7), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - The Wave Drag of Diamond-Shaped Aerofoils at Zero Incidence (8), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Acoustic Analysis in Calculating Supersonic Resistance (9), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Shock Transmission in Beams (10), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Aerofoil Theory of a Flat Delta Wing at Supersonic Speed (11), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Flutter Derivatives of a Wing-Tailpipe Combination (12), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - The Characterization of Algebraic Plane Curves (13), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Note on the Application of the Linearized Theory for Compressible Flow to Transonic Speeds (14), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - The Effect of the Sweepback of Delta Wings on the Performance of an Aircraft at Supersonic Speeds (15), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Interference on a Wing Due to a Body at Supersonic Speeds (16), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Rotary Derivatives of a Delta Wing at Supersonic Speeds (17), 1948 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - On Some Problems of Unsteady Supersonic Airfoil Theory (18), 1948 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Bound and Trailing Vortices in the Linearized Theory of Supersonic Flow, and the Downwash in the Wake of a Delta Wing (19), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - On Source and Vortex Distributions in the Linearized Theory of Steady Supersonic Flow (20), 1948 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - The Aerodynamic Derivatives with Respect to Sideslip for a Delta Wing with Small Dihedral at Supersonic Speeds (21), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Numerical Solutions of Integral Equations (22), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - On Non-Associative Systems (23), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - On the Integration on Hyperbolic Differential Equations (24), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - On Functional Transformations and Summability (25), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Les Rapports Entre le Calcul Déductif et L'Interprétation Sémantique D'un Système Axiomatique (26), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - On the Application of Symbolic Logic to Algebra (27), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Wave Reflection Near a Wall (28), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - On Axiomatic Systems Which Possess Finite Models (29), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Aerofoil Theory for Swallow Tail Wings of Small Aspect Ratio (30), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - L'Application de la Logique Formelle aux Mathématiques (31), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Non-Uniform Supersonic Flow (32), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Flow Round Compound Lifting Units (33), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Core-Consistency and Total Inclusion for Methods of Summability (34), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - On Some Problems of Unsteady Airfoil Theory (35), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - On Predicates in Algebraically Closed Fields (36), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Note on an Embedding Theorem for Algebraic Systems (37), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Mixed Problems for Hyperbolic Partial Differential Equations (38), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Metamathematical Considerations on the Relative Irreducability of Polynomials (39), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - On Ordered Fields and Definite Functions (40), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Aperçu Metamathématique sur les Nombres Réels (41), 1956 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Further Remarks on Ordered Fields and Definite Functions (42), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - A Result on Consistency and its Application to the Theory of Definition (43), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Note on a Problem of Littenkin (44), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Mathematical Interpretation of Formal Systems (45), 1955 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Theory of Models (46), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Solution of a Problem by Erdos-Gillman-Henriksen (47), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - On the Motion of Small Particles in a Potential Field of Flow (48), 1956 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Wave Propogation in a Heterogeneous Elastic Medium (49), 1955 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Transient Stresses of Beams of Variable Characteristics (50), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Some Problems of Definability in the Lower Predicate Calculus (51), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Syntactical Transformations (52), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - On the Representation of Hebrand Functions in Algebraically Closed Fields (53), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Relative Model Completeness and the Elimination of Quantifiers (54), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Relative Model Completeness and the Elimination of Quantifiers (55), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Proving a Theorem (as Done by Man, Logician, or Machine) (56), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Applications to Field Theory (57), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Outline of an Introduction to Mathematical Logic I, II, III, IV (58), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Solution of a Problem of Tarski (59), 1959 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - On the Concept of a Differentially Closed Field (60), 1959 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Obstructions to Arithmetical Extension and the Theorem of Los and Suszko (61), 1959 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Algèbre Différentielle à Valeurs Locales (62), 1959 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Local Differential Algebra (63), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Local Differential Algebra—the Analytic Case (with S. Halfin) (64), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - On the Mechanization of the Theory of Equations (65), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Elementary Properties of Ordered Abelian Groups (66), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Recent Developments in Model Theory (67), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Model Theory and Non-Standard Arithmetic (68), 1959 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - On the Construction of Models in Essays on the Foundations of Mathematics (69), 1961 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - On the D Calculus for Linear Differential Equations with Constant Coefficients (70), 1961 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Non-Standard Analysis (71), 1961 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - A Note on Embedding Problems (72), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Airfoil Theory Chapter 72 (73), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Modern Mathematics and Secondary Schools (74), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - A Basis for the Mechanization of the Theory of Equations (75), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - On the Mechanization of the Theory of Numbers (76), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Complex Function Theory over Non-Archimedian Fields (77), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Local Partial Differential Algebra (78), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - On Languages Which are Based on Non-Standard Arithmetic (79), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - On Symmetric Bimatrix Games (80), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Some Remarks on Threshold Functions (81), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - On Generalized Limits and Linear Functionals (82), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Random-Access Stored Program Machines, An Approach to Programming Languages (83), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Between Logic and Mathematics (84), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Formalism 64 (85), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - On the Theory of Normal Families (86), 1965 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Topics in Non-Archimedean Mathematics (87), 1965 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Solution of An Invariant Subspace Problem of K. T. Smith and P. R. Halmos (88), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - A New Approach to the Theory of Algebraic Numbers (89), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - On Some Applications of Model Theory to Algebra and Analysis (90), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Non-Standard Theory of Dedkind Rings (91), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Non-Standard Arithmetic (92), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Multiple Control Computer Models (93), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - The Metaphysics of the Calculus (94), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Some Thoughts on the History of Mathematics (95), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Model Theory (96), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - On Flexural Wave Propagation in Nonhomogeneous Elastic Plates (97), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Topics in Nonstandard Algebraic Number Theory (98), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - A Set-Theoretical Characterization of Enlargements (99), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Germs (100), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Problems and Methods of Model Theory (101), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Compactification of Groups and Rings, and Non-Standard Analysis (102), 1968 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Completing Theories by Forcing (103), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - From a Formalist's Point of View (104), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Elementary Embeddings of Fields of Power Series (105), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Forcing in Model Theory (106), 1971 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Infinite Forcing in Model Theory (107), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Forcing in Model Theory (108), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - On the Notion of Algebraic Closedness for Noncommutative Groups and Fields (109), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 132)
    - Applications of Logic to Pure Mathematics; A Brief Survey (110), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - Algebraic Function Fields and Non-Standard Arithmetic (111), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Inductive Theories and Their Forcing Companions (112), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - The Non-Standard Lambda: 0 4/2 (x): Model I and II (113), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Some Limit Theorems on the Cores of Large but Finite Exchange Economies (114), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Generic Categories (115), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - On the Real Closure of a Hardy Field (116), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - On Bounds in the Theory of Ideals (117), 1969 (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Model Theory as a Framework for Algebra (118), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 141a)
    - Function Theory on Some Nonarchimedean Fields (119), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 14lb)
    - Ordered Differential Fields (120), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 142)
    - Non-Standard Points on Algebraic Curves (121), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 143)
    - Metamathematical Problems (122), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 144)
    - Standard and Nonstandard Number Systems (123), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 145)
    - Numbers—What Are They and What Are They Good For? (124), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 146)
    - Nonstandard Arithmetic and Generic Arithmetic (125), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 147)
    - A Note on Topological Model Theory (126), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - A Decision Method for Elementary Algebra and Geometry—Revisited (127), 1974 (Box 10, Folder 149)
    - Enlarged Sheaves (128), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 150)
    - The Cores of Large Standard Exchange Economies (129), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 151)
    - Non-Standard Exchange Economies (130), 1971 (Box 10, Folder 152)
    - Concerning Progress in the Philosophy of Mathematics (131), 1973 (Box 10, Folder 153)
    - On the Finiteness Theorem of Siegel and Mahler Concerning Diophantine Equations (132), 1975 (Box 10, Folder 154)
    - Algorithms in Algebra—A Memorial Tribute to Abraham Robinson (133), 1975 (Box 10, Folder 155)
    - On Constrained Denotation (134), 1974 (Box 10, Folder 156)
    - Non-standard Analysis: Material concerning a lecture filmed by the Mathematical Association of America, 1970; 1 (Box 10, Folder 157-158)
      - Film of lecture [PAL format], 1970; 1; 1 videotape (VHS, PAL) (Box 19)
        - Use copy, 1 videotape (VHS) (Box 19U)
  - Articles published in encyclopaedias
    - Mathematical Logic and the Foundations of Mathematics, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 159)
    - Dictionary of Scientific Biography, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 160)
    - Thoughts on the [Root?] Article in Mathematics [Encyclopedia Britannica], 1965 (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Writings not on the published bibliography
    - Royal Aircraft Establishment, Data for Weight Estimation, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - Note on the General Design of T. B. R. Aircraft, 1943 July (Box 11, Folder 163)
    - Linear Transformations of Infinite Sequences and the Theory of the Core, 1946 February-October (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - Logical Field Theory, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 165)